Guide to the Louis Auchincloss Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Louis Auchincloss collection
1966-1981
YCAL MSS 460
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.34
(8 boxes)
The Louis Auchincloss collection contains writings and a 2011 Addition. Writings consist of corrected drafts and proofs for works reflecting the diversity of Auchincloss's literary output from the mid 1960s to 1980s. Works include the following: the novels The Embezzlers (1966), A World of Profit (1968), The Country Cousin (1978), The Cat and the King (1981), and Watchfires (1982); a short story collection, Tales of Manhattan (1987); and a collection of critical essays on women writers, Pioneers and Caretakers (1965). The 2011 Addition contains material dating chiefly from the mid 1980s to 2001, including drafts of additional novels and story collections, such as The Book Class (1984), The Atonement and Other Stories (1997), and Her Infinite Variety (2000), and lecture notes.
Auchincloss, Louis, 1917-2010
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by gift and purchase, 1983-2011. For more information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Louis Auchincloss (1917-2010)
Louis Auchincloss, who attended Yale University (1935-1939) and the University of Virginia Law School (1941), was a prolific author of novels, short stories, criticism, biographies, and other non-fiction work from the early 1950s until shortly before his death in 2010.
Summary information is available in the standard biographical resources.
Scope and Contents
The Louis Auchincloss collection contains writings and a 2011 Addition. Writings consist of corrected drafts and proofs for works reflecting the diversity of Auchincloss's literary output over two decades from the mid 1960s to 1980s. Works include the following: the novels The Embezzlers (1966), A World of Profit (1968), The Country Cousin (1978), The Cat and the King (1981), and Watchfires (1982); a short story collection, Tales of Manhattan (1987); and a collection of critical essays on women writers, Pioneers and Caretakers (1965). The 2011 Addition contains material dating chiefly from the mid 1980s to 2001, including drafts of other novels and collections of stories, such as The Book Class (1984), The Atonement and Other Stories (1997), and Her Infinite Variety (2000), and lecture notes.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Writings, 1966-1981. II. 2011 Addition, [circa 1960s]-2001.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Authors; Auchincloss, Louis, 1917-2010
- Writings, 1966-1981; Series I; 2.09; (5 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  Scope and Contents
  Writings consists of corrected drafts and proofs for several works reflecting the diversity of Auchincloss's literary output over two decades from roughly the mid 1960s to mid 1980s.
  Former call numbers: Za Auchincloss, Uncat Za Ms 220, and Uncat Za Ms 347.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Acquired from various sources.
  - The Cat and the King, setting copy, corrected, undated; 4 (Box 1)
  - The Cat and the King, galley proofs, corrected, 1980-1981; 2 (Box 1)
  - The Country Cousin, draft, typescript, corrected, [1978?]; 2 (Box 1)
  - The Embezzler Part I "Guy", undated; 8 (Box 2)
  - The Embezzler Part II "Rex", undated; 2 (Box 2)
  - The Embezzler Part III "Angelica", undated; 2 (Box 2)
  - The Embezzler Parts I-III, undated (Box 2)
  - The Embezzler, setting copy, undated (Box 3)
  - Pioneers and Caretakers, drafts, autograph, corrected, undated (Box 3)
  - Tales of Manhattan, autograph and typescript, corrected, undated; 2 (Box 3)
  - Tales of Manhattan, autograph and typescript, corrected, undated (Box 4)
  - Watchfires, drafts, typescript, corrected, [circa 1981]; 2 (Box 4)
  - Watchfires, galley proof, "author's marked set", 1981 (Box 4)
  - Watchfires, galley proofs, corrected, 1981; 3 (Box 5)
  - A World of Profit, draft, typescript, [1966]; 3 (Box 5)
- 2011 Addition, [circa 1960s]-2001; Series II; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by title and/or supplied heading.
  The 2011 Addition contains partial drafts to novels and collections of stories, as well as lecture notes, dating from roughly the 1960s to 2001.
  Purchased from Glenn Horowitz Bookseller, Inc. on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2011.
  - The Anniversary and Other Stories, drafts, autograph and typescript, corrected, undated (Box 6)
  - The Atonement and Other Stories, drafts, autograph, corrected, undated; 2 (Box 6)
  - The Book Class, novel, drafts, autograph and typescript, corrected, undated; 2 (Box 6)
  - Exit Lady Masham, novel, drafts, autograph and typescript, corrected, undated (Box 6)
  - "Gore Vidal--Louis Auchincloss Letters," proof (photocopy), 1995 July 21 (Box 7)
  - Her Infinite Variety, novel, drafts, autograph, corrected, undated (Box 7)
  - "Ideas for Stories," drafts, autograph and typescript, undated (Box 7)
  - "Lecture Notes," autograph and typescript, corrected, undated (Box 7)
  - "The Man Behind the Book," essay, draft (incomplete), autograph, undated (Box 7)
  - "NYU James--Wharton Lecture Notes," autograph and typescript, 1995, undated (Box 7)
  - [NYU Lecture Notes], autograph and typescript, corrected, 1995, undated (Box 7)
  - "Roosevelt Notes," autograph and typescript, corrected, 2001, undated (Box 7)
  - "The Styles the Man," essay, draft, autograph, corrected, undated (Box 7)
  - "Tales of Yesteryear," stories, drafts, autograph and typescript, corrected, undated; 2 (Box 7)
  - A World of Profit, novel, draft, typescript, [circa 1960s]; 3 (Box 8)
  - Untitled, drafts, autograph, corrected, undated (Box 8)